Ms. Torres, congratulations to you.
Our second inductee into the Cleveland
International Hall of Fame tonight
is Andy Chicolis.
>> [applause]
>> The first Greek
to be inducted into the Cleveland
International Hall of Fame.
He will be inducted by Mr. Lou Frangos,
the chairman of the Frangos Group,
president of the Greek Garden
Association of Cleveland. Mr. Frangos,
come on up.
>> [applause]
>> So, thank you all.
It's an honor to be up here to
to be able to introduce
Andy, but what I'm going to say in 2
minutes
won't suffice. Uh uh
there's a program book
which is a little more elaborate and
will tell you a little bit more about
Andy and what a wonderful person he is,
but
my brief, very briefly,
Good evening, everyone.
Uh
what a joy it is to be celebrating here
with you tonight
for uh
the
class this 2026 class of the Hall of
Fame.
It's a special honor for me to introduce
Andy Chicolis, the first Greek American
inducted into this esteemed hall.
>> [cheering]
[applause]
>> Uh
I have known Andy for decades, and I can
tell you he's one of those rare
individuals
who somehow manages to do everything and
do it well.
Artist, mentor, preservationist,
[snorts]
community leader,
and somehow still finds the time to be
genuinely kind and humble human being,
which frankly is the most important
part.
Whether serving as president of the
Hellenic Preservation Society,
working alongside his wonderful wife
Faith
at the Greek Garden Association, where
they helped lead the complete
restoration of the Greek Cultural
Garden,
whether preserving historic iconography,
organizing unique exhibits of the
Cleveland Museum of Art, or creating his
own studio, or mentoring students across
the globe from Italy, Japan, Taiwan, and
right here in Cleveland, Ohio,
Andy brings the same thing to everything
he does, a self- a selfless passion to
make the world a better
better place than he found it.
There is a quote attributed to
Dostoevsky,
"Beauty will save the world."
Andy doesn't just believe that, he lives
it.
But as meaningful as his work has been,
I would argue that Andy's greatest
impact
isn't in the art he's created or the
institutions he's helped build.
It's in the people he's inspired,
the students he's mentored, and the
countless lives he's touched along the
way.
At his core, Andy is a family man who
carries forward the values
installed in him by his parents, a deep
love, a strong work ethic, and a rich
blending of his Slovenian and
Greek heritage,
with special devotion to the Greek
traditions.
Those roots help shape the man we're
honoring tonight.
And if you ever spent a few minutes with
Andy, you'd know he just doesn't create
beauty, he brings it out in others.
So tonight, it's my privilege to
introduce the man who not only is
deserving of this honor, but has quietly
been earning it for a lifetime.
As we say in Greek,
Axios.
Please join me in welcoming Andy
Chipalos.
>> [applause]
[laughter]
>> I want to thank Lou for the kind
introduction.
And to thank the International
Hall of Fame Committee for this
recognition.
And congratulations
to my fellow inductees.
My father immigrated from Greece, the
island of Evia, Stropones, a hilltop
village. He worked hard, chef, owner of
a few restaurants throughout his career,
and married my mother who was of
Slovenian heritage.
She adopted the Greek traditions and
even mastered the Greek language.
I was fortunate enough to have a broader
view of two ethnic backgrounds growing
up.
Cleveland, my home, is where I was first
introduced to a mixture of different
ethnic families,
Eastern European, Jewish, Italian, etc.
Ethnic identity became a normal way of
life for me.
A mixture of different cultures all
learning from each other.
My exposure to the different ethnic
ethnicities sparked an interest in
foreign study and the chance to further
my educational experiences.
I also had an early interest in
architecture and art
which prompted me to explore studio art
and art history
with sculpture becoming my study major.
Looking first to study locally, but then
I considered European opportunities.
France, Italy, England. I determined
Italy would provide me with the best
opportunity to continue my interest and
pursuit of visual arts.
Italy represented to me a cultural
bridge, historically speaking.
I was fortunate enough to receive my
advanced education in Italy after being
accepted into the Academy of Fine Arts
in Florence, Italy.
I made a trip to Europe on a freighter,
14 days ocean travel,
landing in Greece and then moving to
Italy
at the cost of $175
in 1960
in the '60s. Mind-boggling.
My first academic year started in the
fall of 1996
when Florence experienced the historic
flood in November of that year.
Needless to say, my studies were
interrupted briefly, about 2 weeks
before the university resumed classes.
Everyone who was able to able did
whatever they could to help with the
recovery. I still remember carrying
damaged paintings from the
Uffizi Museum to the Pitti Palace, which
was on the higher ground for safe
storage.
And helping with the transportation of
waterlogged books from the Biblioteca.
They were ultimately transported to
Città di Castello and placed in tobacco
chambers to begin the drying process.
Unfortunately, many did not survive.
This disaster resulted in the
international community coming together
to help restore the damage done to the
works of art, sculptures, and
architecture.
The impact to art conservation is still
being felt today.
But one cannot forget the loss of life
that resulted from this disaster.
After my formal studies in Florence, I
was accepted as assistant working in the
studio of Arnaldo Pomodoro in Milan.
I was able to experience the work
resulting in his one-man exhibitions in
London, New York, and Milan.
Arnaldo Pomodoro first became
internationally recognized for his
sculpture
when he won the Venice Biennale in 1956.
Arnaldo passed away in June of last year
at the age of 98.
My time in Italy provided me with the
chance to study the dynamics of the 14th
century Florence experience and Milan
offered
and is considered the little New York of
Europe, more cosmopolitan and
industrial.
Upon returning to Cleveland, I joined
the staff of the Cleveland Museum of Art
and eventually became an associate
curator of the extensions division.
This department was started in 1914
prior to the opening of the Cleveland
Museum of Art to the public in 1916.
As a commitment as a commitment to art
education,
the department's collection of over
16,000 objects was used for educational
programming programs covering all media
and eras of Western and Asian art.
This collection on its own could be a
standalone museum in any city in the
United States.
It included a range of materials from
folk arts to Dutch ceramics, African
masks, Eskimo art, etc.
Our projects included lending European
folk art textiles to the Robertson
Center for the Arts and Sciences in
Binghamton, New York to support the
exhibition
Goddesses
and their offspring, 19th and 20th
century Eastern European embroideries.
And organizing Flying Images, A Child's
View, which was an exchange of drawings
of daily life between the elementary
students of the Cleveland school system
and Odawara, Japan.
Other extension exhibitions held at the
Cleveland Museum of Art frequently
highlighted Cleveland's cultural
heritage
with notable shows such as Progressive
Vision, The Planning of Downtown
Cleveland, 1903 to 1930,
The Age of Elegance, 1880 to 1914,
and The Order of Things, A History of
the Column.
I was a guest lecturer at the Taiwan
Museum of Art discussing collections and
educational outreach programs.
In the late '80s, one of our department
volunteers and a member of the museum's
Junior Council, Mrs. Helen Collis,
>> [cheering]
[applause]
>> And I were asked by the CMA board to
support the exhibition Holy Image, Holy
Space: Icons and Frescoes from Greece.
We formed a committee representing four
local Greek churches, which energized
the community and raised significant
financial support for the exhibition.
This group became the nucleus for the
Hellenic Preservation Society of
Northeast Ohio, an organization
dedicated
an organization dedicated to promoting
Hellenism and Greek culture.
As a founding member of HPS, I was
introduced to the Greek Cultural Garden
by Mr. Pete Katanis.
He was the Cultural Garden Federation
Greek Garden representative. After
viewing the garden and understanding its
historical importance, HPS undertook the
responsibility of the renovation and
replanting of the garden, becoming the
first ethnic organization to undertake
responsibility for its ethnic garden.
Everyone here who is involved with their
garden knows and understands the work
that is involved in restoration and the
ongoing maintenance.
We, HPS, approached this project as if
we were restoring a fine work of art,
being certain to do no harm.
We selected landscape architect Mr. Jim
McKnight
to develop a new landscape plan based
off the original garden plan.
Then the work began.
Funds were raised and a block grant was
received to repair the stone
infrastructure,
replanting with the help of KeyBank's
Neighbors Make a Difference Day,
and new urns were
uh constructed and adjacent to the
poet's bench on the west slope.
We secured the services of Mr. Sal
Buscemi,
stone specialist, for the stone
infrastructure.
His father was one of the original stone
masons that worked on the gardens during
their early construction.
Weekly, volunteers helped with ongoing
garden maintenance,
planting, spring, fall cleanup.
While I can't remember everyone, we
should recognize the Gates Mills
Horticultural School, whose students
worked here to gain some practical
experience.
Helen Janusa, Mike Kapourales, Gus
Poulos, Duke and Gail Perry Yojanis.
And we can't say enough about the
lunches Gail would pack.
She made certain there was enough food
for all of the volunteers working on
that day. And probably the person who
volunteered most often was Jimmy Watson,
and there are many others who I know
I am failing to mention.
Volunteer time was not restricted to
work. We always found time to strengthen
friendships with each other and the
community.
HPS was instrumental in planning and in
in the installation of new flag poles
for the gardens, funded by the Cleveland
Cultural Garden Federation, which was
undertaken in preparation for the city's
bicentennial.
In 1996, the Greek community hosted the
Cultural Gardens One World Day
celebration.
An official ceremony was held at the
Greek Garden, and in honor of the city's
birthday, the newly renovated garden was
rededicated and presented to Mayor
Michael R. White.
Through our commitment, it became
apparent that there should be new
efforts to encourage more ethnic
communities to become involved and
possibly establish new gardens.
As was the hopes of HPS when undertaking
this project, the new gardens would be
realized. The India garden was dedicated
in 2005.
It was the first garden in 20 years
since the Chinese garden was dedicated
in 1985.
Since then, a number of new gardens have
been established. I won't attempt to
name them
for fear of forget forgetting one, but I
think the number is either 10 or 11.
Needless to say, the cultural gardens
continue to grow.
It was during this period that Richard
Konisiewicz, assistant to the mayor of
Michael R. White, shared an early
drawing of the original cultural gardens
at one of the Cultural Garden Federation
meetings.
At the bottom of the page in the center
was an illustration of a freeze.
Although I didn't realize its importance
at the time, it was enough to make me
start some research.
Research began on the freeze and found
that it was conceived by sculptor Andrew
T. Teggaris in 1939.
The image entitled The Gift of Greece to
Civilization
was adopted as the letterhead of the
Grecian Garden Association at that time.
34 immortals immortals depicted in the
freeze were selected by the artist in
collaboration with Dr. J. J. Mussoff
of Case School of Applied Science and
Professor C. P. Bill of the Classics
Department of Western Reserve
University.
These two institutions subsequently
merged and are today are known as Case
Western Reserve University.
Proposals were put together on what
effort it would take to fully realize
the freeze as originally planned
and presented to the Hellenic
Preservation Board.
We researched potential stone carvers
and identified Mr. Nicholas Fairplay as
the most qualified
being born and educated in his craft in
Great Britain. We are pleasantly
surprised to find him here in our own
backyard.
As we all know, projects of this
magnitude take a while to be realized.
In 2022, responsibility for the Greek
Cultural Garden was transferred to newly
formed Greek Garden Association of
Cleveland under the leadership of Mr.
Lou Frangos, which HPS
continues with its support.
I am pleased to say
that through his efforts and belief in
the project as its historic value and
those of James Primes and many more
individuals within the Greek community
and beyond. And I do apologize for
failing to mention everyone.
Funds have been raised and we are
confident that the freeze will be
installed in the not too distant future.
To conclude, I once again am honored for
this recognition. Thank you.
Oh,
certainly.
>> [sighs]
>> Mr. Nikolas
Mr. Nikolas, congratulations to you.